你好黑客
hello hackers
我是Yan，欢迎来到pwn学院
i'm Yan welcome to pwn college
在这个视频中
and in this video
我们将讨论数据
we are going to be talking about data
该视频是汇编课的一部分
this video is part of our Assembly crash course
如果你是直接看的这个视频
if you're just seeing this video out of context
建议回到汇编系列课程的开头看
go back and start at the beginning of the Assembly crash course
好的
all right
我们开始讲数据
let's talk about some data
所有的道路都通向CPU
recall that all roads lead to the cpu
CPU只理解二进制代码1和0
recall that the cpu only understands binary code ones and zeros
我们深入研究一下
so let's dig in
二进制，1和0，是什么
what is binary ones and zeros
二进制是以2为基数的数制
binary is the number system of base 2
这是数学概念
originally mathematically
这是
and this is the kind of
西方文明中由Thomas Harriet描述的
the western world described by Thomas Harriet
可能也有其它人
and possibly by these other people
大约在16到17世纪左右
roughly at a similar time between the 16th and 17th centuries
而其他文明在更早的时候就知道了
it was known earlier by other civilizations
早很多，如同大多数这类事情一样
much earlier as most of these sort of things are
但现在我们用它来赋能YouTube视频
but now we're using it to power our YouTube videos
这很有趣
which is fun
好的
all right
一个二进制数称为一位
so a binary digit is called a bit
顺便说一下，你可能已经知道这些了
you probably know all this by the way
我只是想确保
i just want to make sure that
每个人都有坚实的基础
we have a solid footing for everybody
这样才可以继续好好学汇编
so that you can move forward and learn the crap out of assembly
好的
all right
基于十进制数数时
and you know as you count up with base ten
是这样数的0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
you go 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
然后在9后面的数字
and then the number after 9
需要两位数
requires two digits
1 0 数字10
1 0 number ten
到了二进制
in binary
这样 0 1
you go 0 1
然后马上就到了10
and then right away you have 10
因为没有字符2
because there is no 2
你可以在右边看到
so you can see on the right here
十进制值
the decimal values
以及它们的二进制表示
and their associated binary representation
这里有个笔误
and i have a typo here
24不小心打成了14
instead of 24 i have 14 by accident
十进制中只有一个14
there's only one 14 in decimal
23后面的数字显然是24
the number after 23 is 24 obviously
但是你可以发现
but you can kind of see that
二进制和十进制的表达方式是一样的
binary represents things same way as decimal does
顺便说一下
by the way a fun trick
如果你用手指数的话
if you count on your fingers
用十进制能数
and you do it in base 10
能数到10
you can count to 10
但要是用二进制
if you do it in base 2
你可以数到2的10次方
you can count to 2 to the 10
因为你有10位可供使用
because you have 10 bits that you can set at will
比如，你只用5根手指
and so you can see with just 5 fingers
甚至只用4根手指
or just 4 fingers even
就能一直数到15
let's say i could count to 15 by holding up different fingers
但有时可能数错
but at some point you'll accidentally flip someone off
我们继续
let's dive onwards
这就是数学意义上的二进制
so that's binary in the mathematical sense
当然计算机使用二进制
of course computers speak binary
为什么使用二进制
why do they speak binary
因为逻辑门
well because of logic gates
因为这样容易造
because it's easy to build
第一节课讲的逻辑门
a logic gate that we talked about back in the first lecture in this module
用1和0构建逻辑门很容易
it's easy to build a logic gate with 1s and 0s
因为这样逻辑简单
because that makes logic easy
现在还有其他的逻辑系统
now there are other logical systems
能支持三进制
that can do base 3 for example ternary logic
三进制计算机是存在的
and ternary computers exist
但主要是玩具和历史旧物
but mostly in like toy and historical form
一般来说
generally speaking
1和0才是正确的选择
ones and zeros are the way to go
更容易对他们形成概念，更易理解
they're just easier they're easier to conceptualize
而且它们更容易建造
and they are easier to build
好极了
boom done all right
如果你有一个10进制的系统
if you had like a system like a base 10 system
想象一下，当你用光来传送数据时
and imagine that that you were using light to send data
不能只看有没有光来
instead of just saying is there light or isn't there light
还得考虑，比如，亮度只有一半
now you have to reason about okay is the light like half on
还是8成光亮
is it like 8
我想说的是
this is one i mean
0，1就非常简单了
but this one zero super easy all right
光，电，所有的东西都很好地反映了这一点
light electricity everything lenses up pretty well to that
所以我们现在用二进制代码
so we use binary code now
作为人类，我们如何与二进制代码交互
how do we as humans interface with binary code
它有很多位
well it just has a lot of digits
这使得它很难处理
making it very difficult to to deal with
如果我告诉你100101111011
if i told you 100101111011
你会说
you're just gonna be like
Yan，你为啥，发生了什么
Yan why are you just what happened right
你遭遇了什么
what is happening to you
但是对于计算机来说，大量的数据是没问题的
but with a computer of course a lot of data is okay
但我们还是需要能够理解
but we still need to be able to reason about the data
计算机处理的数据
that the computer is processing
特别是
especially
这节课要理解的层面
on the level that we're going to be reasoning about it in this course
那么如何表示二进制数据呢
so how do we represent binary data
我们可以用10进制表示
well we could represent it as decimal
我们可以说
we could say hey
1010就是10
you know 1010 that's ten
很好
that's great
或者你说
or you say okay hey
我动一下
let me move myself
每次都是
oh my god every time
我移到这里
let me move myself here
放这里不碍事
where i'm not in the way
我们拿到个数字
we could say okay hey we got a number
11000000
哦，我想
oh i think i don't know
即128(口误)
and that's you know 128
这些你能都记住
you can memorize all these
但这很难
but it's gonna be difficult to deal with
所以十进制不是很好
so decimal is not great
另一个原因是
and another way of saying this
很多整数不对齐
is like a lot of like the round numbers don't line up
你看
i mean you see
这似乎是一个整数
this seems like a very round number
二进制看，这似乎是一个整数
但十进制看，它是240
but it's just 240
如果你接触的多
i mean yeah if you work with computers long enough
你能认出这些常见数字
you start recognizing these common numbers
但当你放大数字
but once you kind of scale up to bigger and bigger numbers
就能难了
it becomes difficult
有人就意识到
so someone realized somewhere along the way that
如果是2的n次方进制
if you use a base that is a power of two
如4、8、16进制，等等
base four eight sixteen etc etc
就可以
then we can actually
用这些进制的一个数字清晰地表示二进制的多个数字
represent multiple binary digits in one of these digits cleanly
10进制的一个数字能表示大概3.几bit
base 10 represents like three point something digits per base 10 digit
这很奇怪
that's really weird
而一个8进制数字正好能表示3bit
whereas base 8 represents exactly three digits
一个16进制数字能表示4bit
base 16 represents exactly four digits
所以用八进制或者十六进制
and so use octo base 8 or hexadecimal base 16
表示二进制数
to represent binary code
而不用10进制
instead of base 10
在右边
and here it is on the right
你可以看到这个1111 0000
and so you can see with this 1111 0000
是f0
hey that's f 0
当然
of course
16进制有16个字符
hexadecimal has 16 digits
10进制只有10个字符
we only have 10 digits available in base 10
就是我们熟悉的数字
and that's the digits we know and love
所以我们用字母填充它们
and so we pad them with letters
十六进制中9后面的数是a
so hexadecimal the number after nine is a
然后b，然后c，然后d，然后e，然后f
then b then c then d then e then f
F转换成十进制是15
f translates to 15 in decimal
然后是0x10
and then after that it's 0x10
已经可以看出来
and you can already see it
0x10对齐的很漂亮
0x10 it lines up beautifully
这里一堆0
a bunch of zeros here
这里也一堆0
boom bunch of zero there
这些大的整数都对齐了
now all of these big round numbers line up well
比8进制还好看
a little better even than octo
有些地方会用八进制
and there are places where we use octo base 8
但十六进制才是王道
but hexadecimal is king
这就是我们显示数据的方式
that's how we display data
CPU用二进制看数据
the cpu sees it as binary code or binary numbers
我们通常用16进制看数据
we see it as hexadecimal numbers typically
酷
awesome
我们继续
let's move on
现在你们都知道十六进制了
and now you all know hexadecimal
这就是数字
that's numbers
那文本呢?
what about text
在你看这张幻灯片的时候
at some point you looking at this slide
它会显示文本
and it shows you text
而不是显示一堆十六进制数
not showing you a bunch of hexadecimal
我们表示文本的方式是用不同的编码
well the way that we express text is in a different encoding
基本上我们使用的文本编码是ASCII
basically the text encoding that we use is ASCII
实际上是ASCII的扩展，称为utf8
an expansion of ASCII actually called utf8
这种文本编码赋能了大多数网页
that's the text encoding that powers most of the web
utf8的前身
and the precursor to utf8
它被称为美国信息交换标准代码
which is called the American standard code for information interchange
是在60年代还是60年代末创作的
was created in like the 60s the late 60s or something
它规定了如何使用7bit进行编码
and it specifies how to encode using 7 bits
基本上就是键盘上的字母
basically the letters that are on your keyboard
如果你有英文键盘
if you have an English keyboard
基本上是小写大写英文字母拉丁字母
but basically lower case uppercase English letters Latin letters
主要是英文字母
but you know specifically in this case English letters
数字和一堆常见的特殊字符
the digits and then a bunch of common special characters
右边是一个ASCII表
this on the right is an ASCII table
每次移动我都
every freaking time moving me
右边是一个ASCII表
on the right here is an ascii table
查看方式是
and the way that you look it up
左边是第一个16进制数
is the left side is the first hex digit
不，错了
no my bad
顶部的2到7是第一个十六进制数
the top is the first hex digit from two through seven
左边是第二个 十六进制数字
the left side is the second hex digit
所以0x41在ascii编码中是字母A
so hex 41 encodes in ascii to the letter A
所以当你看到这个A的时候
and so whenever you see like this A right here
大写字母A
the capital letter A
在一个bit风暴中
somewhere over the crazy storm of bits
飞到你的无线卡中
that flew over into your wireless card
给你展现出这个幻灯片
to give you this slide
其中有个0x41表示字母A
there was a hex 41 representing that letter A
很大程度上
for the most part
你可以便捷地看成0x40加上字母的序号
you can kind of see these shortcuts hex 40 plus the number of the letter
A是第一个字母，B是第二个字母，以此类推
a's the first letter b's the second letter and so forth
这是大写字母
is uppercase letters
(小写则)0x60加序号
hex 60 plus the letter
0x61是a,0x65是e，等等
so hex 61 is a hex 65 is e etc
数字是0x30加数字
digit representations is hex 30 plus the digit
0x35是数字5
hex 35 is the representation of the digit 5
像这个
like this
等等
and so on
你还会认识一些其它的特殊字符
there are some other special characters that you will learn to recognize
你可能会知道2f是正斜杠
you will learn that 2f is forward slash probably
好吧，我讲的ASCII
all right i mentioned ascii started out
是以美国为中心的
very kind of you know America focused
它被称为美国信息交换标准
it's actually called American standard of information interchange
它随着网络的全球化而进化
it evolved when the web became global
我们需要通用的方式来表达任何语言
and we needed common ways to express any language
它后来演变成了utf8
it evolved into utf8
我记得是通用文本格式，不确定
i think Universal Text Format don't quote me on that one
utf8基本上就是ASCII码
so utf8 basically is ascii
如果第一位置为1
but if the top bit is set
它是8位编码格式（ascii是7位）
it's a 8 bit format initially
如果第一位置为1
if the top bit is set
它会读更多位
it reads more bits
若读的字节首位是1
and those top bits are set
它会读更多
it reads more and more bits right
所以它可以表示很多东西
so it can represent a lot of things
不同语言的符号
a lot of different language glyphs
还有很多表情符号
and also a lot of emojis
这就是所有表情符号的来源
that's where all your emojis come from
Utf8非常重要
utf8 is very important
它来自ASCII码
it came from ascii
可以告诉你的朋友
tell your friends all right
但是在这门课上
but in this class
当我们看
mostly when we look at
我们要看的程序
the types of program that we'll be looking at
甚至以后你看到的会处理英文文本的程序
and even when you look at programs that deal with English text
ASCII仍然是常用的
ascii is still your go to typically
当然，还有其它文本格式
of course there are other ways to format text
我们现在就来讨论
that we'll talk about right now actually all right
8位编码
8 bits encode
实际上是7位，但utf8会用8位编码一个字母
actually 7 bits but 8 bits with utf8 encode a single letter
现在8位就是我们所说的一个字节
now 8 bits is what we call a byte nowadays
从历史上看，这与文本编码有关
historically this is tied to text encoding
一字节有8位的原因
the reason that we have 8 bits to a byte
一个字节就是位的集合
a byte just being a collection of bits
确切地说是8个位
8 of them to be precise
就是因为文本
is because of text
其实，一字节可以是任意位
basically you can have any number of bits to a byte
我遇到过有的架构有很奇怪的位数
i've worked with architecture with insane amounts of bits
一个字节有很多位
a lot of bits to a byte
或者很少的位，等等
little bit to a byte etc etc etc
这些都是最晚上世纪60年代末的古董
these were all ancient from the like the late 60s was the most recent one
这是有原因的
there's a reason for that
在60年代
in the 60s
ASCII码创建时
while also being involved in the creation of ASCII
由于某种原因，IBM创建了另一个EBC DIC
for some reason IBM created another EBC DIC
它是另一种文本格式
another format for expressing text
还有一些不令人满意的东西
there was some wonky other thing
基本上相同的字母有不同的表示
i mean basically the same letters in different configurations
所以0x41不是大写的a了
so a hex 41 wouldn't be capital A
它可能是一些随机的垃圾
it would be some random junk
实际上，由于某种原因，我上周末在看EBC DIC
and i actually for some reason was looking at EBC DIC last weekend
所以我大概能想出这个表
so i could kind of picture the table in my head
但不清楚0x41是什么
but not enough to tell you what 0x41 is
我记得字母在左下角
i think the letters were on the bottom left
不管怎样
anyways
EBC DIC是一种8位文本编码
EBC DIC was an 8 bit text encoding
1963年，ibm的大型机已经非常普及
and ibm's mainframes were very widespread by 1963
所以他们偶然创造了8位字节
and so they kind of created the 8 bit byte by accident
ASCII取代了EBC DIC
ASCII replaced EBC DIC
但8位是一字节的概念保留了下来
but you know the concept of 8 bits to a byte stuck
每个现代架构都使用8位字节
every modern architecture uses 8 bit bytes
技术上讲，没有官方定义一个字节就是8位
technically speaking a byte is not i think officially defined as 8 bits
如果你想要非常精确的话，这就像一个八进制
that's like an octat if you want to be extremely precise
但只要有人说一字节
but whenever anyone says bytes
意思就是8位
they mean 8 bits
除了特殊情况
except for in various itare situations
所以8位组成一字节
so bits form into 8 bytes
每一个都可以保存一些值
each of which can hold some values
或者是一些文本，看成文本的话
or you know in code some text if you look at it as text
我们如何把字节组成字
okay now how do we group bytes into words
又一次
and again
又弄错了
oh my god and again i'm doing the wrong thing
我又挡住了幻灯片的文本
and again i am covering slide text
抱歉，好的
i'm sorry about that um all right
字节能组成字
bytes get grouped into words
所以我说x86是64位架构时
so when i tell you x86 is a 64 bit architecture
我真正的意思是
what i actually mean is that
X86处理位时
x86 deals with bits
8位为一字节
8 bits to a byte
8字节为一个字
8 bytes to a word
字长为64位
for a word length of 64 bits
它一次处理64位
and it deals with 64 bits at a time
这有一些历史上的奇怪之处
now this has some historic oddities
因为我们并不总是使用64位架构
because we didn't always have 64 bit architectures
所以很久以前
so once upon a time
我们只有8位架构
we just had 8 bit architectures
一个字节就是一个字节
and so a byte was just a byte
然后我们有了16位架构
then we had 16 bit architectures
但一字节仍然是8位
but a byte was still 8 bits
我们需要用别的名字来称呼它
and we said okay well we need some other name to call it
就是字
that was a word
然后我们创建了一个32位架构
then we created a 32 bit architecture
然后我们说好吧
so then we said okay well
16位是一个字
but 16 bits is a word
所以32位是一个双字
so 32 bits is gonna be a double word
但其他人说
but then other people said okay
字的长度是32位
the word width is 32 bits
32位是一个双字
so 32 bits is gonna be a double word
其他人说，嘿
other people said hey
32位是架构的字长
32 bit is the word length of architecture the word width of architecture
所以16位现在是半个字
so 16 bits is now going to be a half word
就有了重叠
so you have this overlap
所以半字、字都指16位
so like half word could be or word could be both refer to 16 bits
双字、字都指32位
double word or word could both refer to 32 bits
到了64位时
and then when we went to 64 bits
我们会这么说
we'll say that okay you know what
这太疯狂了
this is insane
我们叫它四字
let's just call it a quad word
所以现在最安全的表达方式是
so it is so nowadays the safe way to say things
半字是两字节
half word is two bytes
双字
double word
你可能认为是半字的4倍
which you would think is four times the half word
但不是
but no
半字是两个字节
half word is two bytes
双字是四个字节
double word is four bytes
四字是8字节
quad word is 8 bytes
至少最后一步说得通
at least that last step makes sense
好吧
awesome okay
所以说字的时候
so you know if you want to talk about words
我的建议是要精确
my recommendation be precise
有趣的一点，半个字节称为nibble
also fun fact half of a byte is called a nibble
这个挺有趣的
i just put that in there just for fun
好
okay cool
我们讨论了文本的表示
we talked about expressing text
再谈谈数字的表达
let's talk about expressing numbers
64位体系结构
a 64 bit architecture
64位CPU一般一次可以处理64位
64 bit cpu can reason about 64 bits at a time generally
这就是它的意思
that's what it means
表示它的字长
means its wordwidth
通常是适合它寄存器的长度
amount that typically fits into its registers etc etc
是64位
is 64 bits
现在有其他聪明的方法来处理更多
now there are other kind of clever ways to reason about more
所以现代x86真的很酷
so actually modern x86 is really cool
它有专门的硬件
and it actually has specialized hardware
每次能处理大约512位
to reason about 512 bits at a time
就是64字节
that's 64 bytes
这是很多的数据
that's a lot of data
用它来处理多媒体等等
uses that for stuff like multimedia processing and so forth
好的
all right
所以64位二进制数字可以表示很大范围的值
so 64 binary digits can express an enormous range of values
从最小值0
from 0 at the minimum
到一些酷的数字如 0x539即1337
to some other cool numbers hex 539 is 1337
很有黑客范（3=e，7=t）
that is a very leet number
到最大值2的64次方-1
to the maximum which is 2 to the 64 power minus one
每多一位能表示的范围就翻一倍
so every bit is an additional amount of data that you can convey
如果有1位
if you have one bit
可以表示1或0
you can just say one or zero
只能表示2个值
you can only convey two values
如果有2位
if you have two bits
就可以表达4个值
you can convey four values
0、1、10和11
a 0  a 1 a 10 and a 11
每增加一比特，它就会翻倍
and every additional bit doubles it
一个n位的数字可以表示
so an n bit number can convey
可以编码
can encode can represent
2的n次方个值
two to the n total values
最大值是2^n - 1
and the maximum value is two to the n minus one
从0到2^n - 1
from 0 to 2 to the n - 1
64位整数的最大值是这个
the maximum 64 bit integer is this monstrosity
用十六进制表示成FFFF FFFF FFFF FFFF
and then in hex we represented it as ffff ffff ffff ffff
展开一下
quick sidebar
这让我们思考起来
that will kind of start getting our thinking juices flowing
如果给64位最大值加1，会怎样
what happened if you add one to the maximum 64 bit number
会得到一个65位的数
well you would normally end up with a 65 bit number
如果给1位最大值加1
if you add one to the maximum one bit number
1位最大值为1
the maximum bit numbers one
会得到10
you get 10
这是一个两位的数字
that's a two bit number
但是64位架构装不下65位的数
but the 65th bit doesn't fit in a 64 bit architecture
它会去哪呢
so where does it go
其实不要惊慌
actually don't panic
我们不会失去它
we don't lose it
cpu有地方存储它
the cpu has a special place where it stores it
这个地方
that special place is actually
由任何会产生65位数的操作所共享
shared any operation that will end up making a 65th bit
这第65位会放到一个特殊的盒子中
that 65th bit will get put into this special box
如果你想要它
so if you want to if you want it
要在这之后马上取它
you need to get it right away after that
在我们称之为的溢出之后
after what we call overflow
当你溢出时
where you overflow
操作整数发生溢出时
integer overflow where you do an integer operation
你往一个很大的数加1
you add one to a very large number
最后得到65位数时
and you end up with 65 bits
你就溢出了，超过了最大值
you overflowed the maximum value
当然也有相反的情况
so and of course the inverse happens
当你减去1
when you subtract one
你用0减去1时
you have zero and you subtract one
然后就会下溢
and then you underflow
它以同样的方式保存在那里
and it gets saved the same way
你要保存这多余的一位
you save that extra one
概念上很相似
conceptually similar and go from there
好的
all right
我将在几节课后讨论这个问题
i'll talk about that a couple of lectures from now actually
我们刚说用0减去1
so we just said subtracting one from zero
结果是-1
now that gives us negative one
但我们在这里看的所有数字
but all of the numbers we're looking at here
都是正数
they're very positive numbers
怎么表示负数呢
so how do we talk about negative numbers
好吧
well
冯·诺伊曼架构的那个冯·诺伊曼
John von Neumann of von Neumann architecture fame
前几节课应该听过他了
which you heard about a couple lectures ago
建议使用补码
actually gave a suggestion to use something called 2's complement
这是一个疯狂的想法
it's a crazy idea
他取代了之前的老想法
and it replaces an older idea that said hey
为什么不直接用一位
why don't we just have a bit
最左边的一位
the left most bit here right here
来表示符号，这个数是负的
it'll say that hey this number is negative
这个数是正的
so this number will be positive
00……11是正3
00...11 is positive 3
在8位架构中是1...
but 1 in an 8 bit architecture
但你可以想象64位中是1，更多的0，然后11
which you can imagine 64 bit is just 1 and then way more zeros and then 11
结果是-3
that will be a negative 3
这很好也很简单
that's nice and simple
但它有一个缺点
but it has a drawback
0会有两种不同的表示方法
we have two different representations for 0
+0和-0
we have positive 0 and negative 0
从数学上讲，这是个坏消息
mathematically this is a bad news
我们不想要处理0的两种形式
we don't want to have to deal with two representations of 0
特别是在实现数学运算时
in terms of implementing mathematical operations
还有就是，你做任何运算时
the other thing is that any operation you make
比如加减法等等
like add subtract etc etc
都必须要关注
it has to be aware of
处理的是有符号数还是无符号数
whether it is dealing with signed numbers or unsigned numbers
因为如果有一个0
because if you have a zero
用它减去1
and you subtract one from it
会得到-1
and you end up with negative one
结果就像这样
you're going to end up with this situation
1，一串0，1
one a bunch of zeros negative one
如果是无符号操作
and then if you're only talking about positive numbers
你想表示尽可能多的正数
so you just want as many positive numbers to represent as possible
最大值是255
which means the biggest one is 255
那么0 - 1应该是255
then zero minus one should be 255
所以CPU必须关注有无符号
so your CPUs would have to be signedness aware
必须要有多套指令
you'd have to have multiple instructions
比如一个有符号加法，一个无符号加法
one for doing add sign add unsign
或另一个地方来存储符号
or different sets of places to store signedness
那将是一场噩梦
it would be a nightmare
所以冯·诺伊曼提出了
so von neumann came up with
或者可能在别处发现并提议使用它
or maybe found elsewhere and proposed to use it
一个非常聪明的方法叫做补码
a very clever approach called 2's complement
首先，补码中0只有一种表示
first of all 2's complement has one representation of 0 if 0
这很好也很简单
that's nice and easy
全0即是0
all 0 bits 0
疯狂的是
and the crazy thing is that
负数与正数的表示法相同
negative numbers have the same representation as positive numbers
所以0 - 1结果为全1
so zero minus one is all ones
这既是255也是-1
and that is both 255 and negative 1
如果再减去一
if you subtract another one from that
是11...0
it's all 1 and 1 0
等于254或- 2
it's 254 or negative 2
这样你就可以在大多数情况下不用担心符号了
and so you can do your arithmetic for the most part without worrying about the sign
加减等操作肯定不用担心了
definitely add subtract several others
不用担心数据的符号了
you don't have to worry about the signedness of the data
值都是一样的
it's the same
另一个好处
another benefit
最左边的位仍然是符号位
the left most bit here is still the sign bit
因为所有负数最左边的都是1
because all negative numbers will have that as one
这很好
which is great
缺点是会有点疯狂
now the downside is you'll go a little crazy
为什么这个是-1
because i mean why does this represent negative 1
你能大概看出来
you can kind of see it
为什么这个是-2
why does this represent negative 2
你也许还能看出来
you can still kind of maybe see it
但当你看到任意一堆1和0
but if you look at an arbitrary a bunch of 1s and 0s
你很难分辨出它是什么负数
it's very hard to say what negative number it is
但是如果你把这个值当作正数
but basically if you take this value as a positive number
然后减去256
and you subtract 256 from it
这将是负的
that's going to be the negative
从这个角度来看，是有道理的
it kind of makes sense from that perspective
现在在补码中
now in 2's complement
8位中最小可表达的负数
the smallest expressible negative number in 8 bit
以8位为一字节
for an 8 bit byte
是-128
is negative 128
1后面全是0
it's one followed by all zeros
这在无符号数中是128
this is an unsigned 128
然后是256，哦，不好意思
and then it's 256 oh sorry
如果减去128
if you subtract 128
如果你把它看作一个无符号整数
this if you were looking at it as an unsigned integer
应该是128
would be 128
等等，这对吗?
wait is this right
是的
yes yes yes
如果把它看成一个无符号整数，就是128
if you were looking it at as an unsigned integer would be 128
如果用它减去256
if you subtract 256 from that
最后会得到-128
you end up with -128
这是它在补码中的值
that's its value in two's complement
当你在有符号的情况下考虑它
when you are thinking about it in the context of it being signed
如果-128减去1
if you subtract one from that negative 128
最后得到一个0跟着全是1
you end up with a 0 and all ones
这是一个正数了
that's a positive number now
这是有符号补码表示方法中最大的正数（8位）
the biggest positive number in signed interpretation of two's complement
数据既可以解释为有符号整数
again the data can both be interpreted as signed integer
取值范围为-128 ~ 127
in which case it ranges from -128 to 127
也可以是无符号整数
or an unsigned integer
取值范围为0 ~ 255
in which case it ranges from 0 to 255
很酷
super cool stuff
这实际上是
and this is actually where the
写c代码时
if you've written in c
你可以声明成无符号整型和有符号整型
and you've ??? set unsigned int versus int
默认情况是有符号的
which by default is signed
这就它改变的，是类型
that's what it changes is the types
不是数据操作的类型
not the types of operations performed on the data typically
因为它们对符号是不可知的
because they are agnostic to signedness
而是我们稍后会学到的
but actually as we'll learn later
如何根据这些数据做决定的
how that data is reason about to make decisions
这很酷
which is super cool
总之，补码真的很酷
anyways 2's complement really cool
我们继续
let's move on
好了，最后我们来谈谈字的结构
alright finally let's talk about the anatomy of a word
我们有
so we have a
这是一个32位的字
this is a 32 bit word
我们有一堆比特
we have a bunch of bits
这里用十六进制表示
here it is represented in hex
上面写着酷猫（4=a，7=t，5=s）
this says cool (c001) cats (c475)
我真聪明
very very clever by me
好吧
all right anyways
它们都有名字
so there's a number of names for a number of things
左边的一件东西
one things to the left
屏幕镜像了
yeah mirrored on the screen
总之，左边的是
but anyways things to the left are
最高有效位，最左位，或者叫最高位
the most significant or the left most or the high bits
为什么它们是最有效的呢
now why are they most significant
因为在这些位上做修改，对值的影响最大
because a change in those bits will most change the value of that number
概念上你可以用十进制来考虑
conceptually you can think about it in decimal
如果数字700万
if i have the number 7 million
把最左边的数字改成6，即600万
and i change the left most digit to 6 million
这是一个巨大的差异
that's a huge difference
要是改最右边的
if i change the right most difference
会得到7百万零一
i get 7 million and one
前后差别很小
that's a small difference
因此最右边的位
hence the right most bit
低位，是最低有效位
the low bits are the least significant bits
同样的，有最低有效字节
and you know you have the same least significant byte
最高有效字节
most significant byte
最后一位是最低有效位
the last bit is that most least significant bit
最后一个字节是保存它的字节
the last byte is the byte holding it
首位也一样
same of the first bit
也就是首字节中的符号位
which is also the sign bit in the first byte alright
现在你知道字的组成部分了
now you know the parts of a word
实际上，你现在对数据已经了解很多了
actually you know an enormous amount now about data
以及它存在于的电脑
as it exists inside computers
希望你们已经准备好学习
hopefully you're ready to learn about
计算机如何处理这些数据的了
how computers process these data
再见
see you soon